<?xml version="1.0"?><metadata><idinfo><keywords><theme><themekt>User</themekt><themekey>Glacier Bay</themekey><themekey>Glaciers</themekey><themekey>National Park Service</themekey></theme><place><placekt>None</placekt><placekey>Alaska</placekey><placekey>Canada</placekey></place></keywords><citation><citeinfo><pubinfo><pubplace>University of Alaska Fairbanks</pubplace></pubinfo><pubdate>20110810</pubdate><origin>Anthony Arendt &amp; Justin L. Rich 
401 E, Geophysical Institute
903 Koyukuk Dr
Fairbanks AK 99775-7320 

arendta@gi.alaska.edu
phone: +1 (907) 474-7427
</origin><title>Glacier Bay - 2010 Glacier Extents</title></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>Glaciers cover about 75,000 km2 of Alaska’s land surface, and approximately one-quarter of those glaciers (by area) are located within National Park boundaries.  Most of Alaska’s glaciers have experienced steady recession since the close of the Little Ice Age (~mid 1800).  Recent observations indicate that the rate of recession and glacier thinning has increased over the last decade.

The direct and indirect effect glacier change may have on Alaska ecosystem function is not completely understood.  What is understood, but not well quantified, is that glaciers store a huge amount of fresh water on the landscape.  The release of this “stored water” is a factor of weather and climate and directly affects the productivity of fresh water flow regimes, productivity of coastal marine systems and vegetation communities on the landscape.

This dataset provides outlines of glacier locations at different time periods, information that is required to assess the impacts of glaciers on landscapes and on rates of global sea level change.


</abstract><purpose>The purpose of the glacier inventory project is to produce a comprehensive assessment of glacier ice extent, area, and volume change for glaciers in Alaska national parks. </purpose></descript><timeperd><current>Ground condition</current><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>Sept. 2010</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>As needed</update></status><accconst>None.</accconst><useconst>None. Please check sources, scale, accuracy, currentness and other available information. Please confirm that you are using the most recent copy of both data and metadata.  Acknowledgement of creators would be appreciated.</useconst><spdom><bounding><westbc>-138.65</westbc><eastbc>-135.03</eastbc><northbc>59.70</northbc><southbc>58.23</southbc></bounding></spdom></idinfo><eainfo><overview><eaover>The 4 digit attribute field ‘Code’ is derived from the description given in Paul et. al. (2009) “Recommendations for the compilation of glacier inventory data from digital sources”.

(Table)
Code 	Snow			Calving		Surging		Divides
0	normal			normal		normal		normal
1	hides 5-50% perim	tidewater	reported	uncertain
2	hides &gt; 50% perim	freshwater	signs		compound
3	perennial snowfield	dry		signs &amp; report	ice cap
4	seasonal snowfield	regenerated	-		-
8	spec. rem.		spec. rem.	spec. rem.	spec. rem.
9	not spec.		not spec.	not spec.	not spec.
</eaover></overview></eainfo><dataqual><logic>Features were manually edited to reflect accurate outlines as best possible. Polygons were cleaned using ArcGIS’s geometry repair tools and were also logically tested to help prevent topological errors. </logic><complete>Features represented have not been tested for completeness</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>Data were derived from Landsat ETM+ imagery downloaded from the USGS and are accurate relative to the scenes used.</horizpar></horizpa></posacc><lineage><procstep><procdate>2011</procdate><procdesc>Landsat ETM+ images (LE70590192010259EDC00 &amp; LE70600192010266EDC01) were downloaded from the USGS Earth Explorer http://edcsns17.cr.usgs.gov/NewEarthExplorer/) and run through a de-striping algorithm. This algorithm uses a 7x7 moving window to fill in the missing data based on weighted averages. This does not fix the data but does create a continuous dataset need for the automated analysis. </procdesc></procstep><procstep><procdate>2011</procdate><procdesc>Landsat ETM+ scenes were used to run an automated analysis that used a band 3/ band 5 ratio, a thermal image converted from radiance to surface temperature and NDVI, in order to capture ice extent. This worked well at identifying bear ice but ran into problems with heavily debris covered ice. </procdesc></procstep><procstep><procdate>2011</procdate><procdesc>Extensive manual digitizing of the automated dataset was carried out in order to fix mis-classified areas and capture debris covered ice.</procdesc></procstep><procstep><procdate>2011</procdate><procdesc>The resulting dataset was run through a script (written by Christian Kienholz, University of Bern, 09/18/2009) which delineated glaciers by drainage basin based on the National Elevation Dataset. The resulting basins where then manually edited to fix errors and better represent reality.</procdesc></procstep></lineage></dataqual><distinfo><resdesc>Downloadable Data</resdesc><distliab>Although these data have been processed successfully, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the accuracy or utility of the data on any other system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. It is also strongly recommended that careful attention be paid to the contents of the metadata file associated with these data to evaluate data set limitations, restrictions or intended use. The creators and distributers of the dataset shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein.</distliab></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20110811</metd><metfrd>None</metfrd><metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn><metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv></metainfo><spref><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>8</utmzone><transmer><sfctrmer>0.99960000</sfctrmer><longcm>-135</longcm><latprjo>0.00000000</latprjo><feast>500000.00000000</feast><fnorth>0.00000000</fnorth></transmer></utm></gridsys><planci><plance>coordinate pair</plance><coordrep><absres>0.00001</absres><ordres>0.00001</ordres></coordrep><plandu>meters</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>North American Datum of 1983</horizdn><ellips>Geodetic Reference System 1980</ellips><semiaxis>6378137.000000</semiaxis><denflat>298.257222</denflat></geodetic></horizsys></spref></metadata>